Curriculum Vitae

of

Md. Alomgir Hossain

Mailing Address: Shawra Bazar Pocket gate, Baridhara DOHS, Dhaka

Bangladesh.

Skype: alomgirbd77, Cell: +8801712545003(WhatsApp), +8801710391944

E-mail: alomgir.ru77@gmail.com / alomgir@ti-bangladesh.org

Website: https://circleassociatesbd.org/digital-melhub

Click here to see Visualized CV



PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

In my professional life, I have more than 16 years' successful works experience with RDRS Bangladesh, World Vision Bangladesh, IRRI Bangladesh, Abt Associates and Transparency International Bangladesh (TIB) as Sr. M&E Officer, M&E Officer, M&E Specialist, MEL Coordinator and Deputy Coordinator-Monitoring, Evaluation and Learning respectfully in designing and implementing M&E systems, database management and reporting with different types of beneficiaries especially women and children covering nutrition, water sanitation and hygiene (WASH), Gender, Agriculture and Livelihood, DRR, Research, Good Governance & Social Accountability component. During in my career, I was directly involved with designing, developing TOC, M&E plan and Monitoring tools, executing the M&E system, CLA, conducting the internal data quality assessment & involved the external DQA, involving the baseline, mid-line and end-line survey and formative research studies as required, result framework, CBO assessment and various capacity building for project and Partner staffs. Along the regular activities, I was directly involved in different workshops, meeting, training, data compilation, spot checking, validation and field visit finding sharing at different level. I have excellent methodological skills and knowledge both for qualitative and quantitative methods in the field of M&E and Research. I completed graduation and post-graduation in Statistics from Rajshahi University that enhance my academic knowledge and skills for quantitative and qualitative purposes. I have used the M&E tools to identify continuous programmatic improvement areas and required necessary adaptive management decision making for the betterment of the program interventions at Output and outcome level. Among them, I have more than 12 years' experience in international Organizations as "M&E Officer, M&E Specialist, MEL Coordinator and Deputy Coordinator-MEL" funded by USAID/FCDO, SDC, SIDA, Netherlannds and EU on MEL, MIS, Research, CLA, Nutrition & Health, Food security, Emergency Operations, Good Governance, Anti-corruption and cyclone SIDAR recovery operations. My major job responsibilities were setting up, implementation & coordination of MEL systems and guidelines; developed, managed & updated M&E database including Process Monitoring, Routine Monitoring, Theory of change (TOC), Result Framework and Indicators, Data quality assurance, Kobo collect application; USAID's electronic reporting system, DIS, Track the project's outputs, Capacity Building & Various Reporting with analysis through SPSS/STATA.

CORE EXPERTISE

- Professional M&E Report Writing and Research
- Kobo Toolbox for digital data collection Tools (offline & online)
- Power Bl and Python (Level-1&2) for data Visualization
- MIS and ArcGIS
- Collaborating, Learning and Adapting (CLA) and Data Quality Assessment (DQA)
- Database management and analysis (MS Word, Excel, Power Point, Kobo, PowerBl, Google looker studio, GIS, SPSS, & STATA.)
- Project Management Concepts (Logical Frameworks, Theory of Change & Result Based Management)
- Strategic planning
- Market System Development Strategy (MSDS) & Social Behavior and Communication Change (SBCC)

EDUCATIONAL QUALIFICTIONS

Master of Science (MS) in Statistics, Rajshahi University, 1999 Bachelor of Science (BS) in Statistics, Rajshahi University, 1998

COMPUTER SKILLS

- Advanced knowledge on MS Office suite- MS word, MS excel, Power Point and Data analysis software (SPSS & STATA)
- Advance level knowledge on Operating Systems & different browser
- Mobile application tools developer by using Kobo Toolbox / ODK.
- Python programming language (Level-I & Level-2) for data visualization

LANGUAGE PROFICIENCY

Bangla – native

English - advanced level

RELEVANT WORK EXPERIENCE

Organization: Transparency International Bangladesh (TIB), PACTA Project Position: Deputy Coordinator/Manager-Monitoring, Evaluation and Learning

Duration: January 2023 to Present.

Key Responsibilities:

- Coordinate and support to develop and deliver a robust and technically appropriate MEL system.
- Contribute to develop Theory of Change (ToC), Results Chain Framework (RCF), ensure alignment of MEL plan and framework with agreed outputs and outcomes for achieving project objectives:
- Assist to conduct Data Quality Assessments (DQAs) and prepare relevant reports on regular basis.
- Provide active support to disseminate the learning across divisions and units and creating opportunities for continuous redesigning and readjustments of programs/outputs in project cycle;
- Play active role to conduct the baseline study, evaluations and assessment process for the project;
- Organize frequent pilot learning review to capture the lessons learnt and other reflection sessions with staff and stakeholders;
- Develop knowledge products based on project's learnings and achievements for various stakeholders and platforms (case stories, blogs, articles, briefs, etc.);
- Extend cooperation to MIS team to develop an effective system in line with the MEL system;
- Organize capacity-building activities for project staff to help implement MEL efficiently.
- Prepare the progress reports, both consolidated for submission to management, Board, development partners, relevant government agencies and other stakeholders, in accordance with approved reporting formats.
- Analyze monitoring reports for further use such as, impact evaluation, mid-term and/or other periodic reviews and identify the causes of potential bottlenecks and risks in project implementation.
- Carry out periodic monitoring and technical support visits in project areas to assess progress against agreed MEL system and recommend remedial actions.
- Provide technical support to programme teams including planning, design and implementation of baseline/mid
 line and other data requirements to support programme analysis for further development using monitoring
 tools and instruments.

Key Achievement's: Played leading role in the establishment of Data Management according to RCF, Data Analysis tools, Development MEL Plan, Result Change Framework(RCF), Quarterly and yearly reporting. Conducted monitoring of nine research/studies in 2024 which were carried out by the Research & Policy (R&P) division from lanuary 2022 to June 2023.

Organization: Abt Associates, USAID funded Bangladesh Nutrition Activity (BNA)

Position: Monitoring, Evaluation and Learning Coordinator/ Manager

Duration: April 2019 to January 2023

Key Responsibilities:

- Assist in designing and implementing of monitoring evaluation and learning (MEL) strategies to collect monitoring data through appropriates tools in the projects target districts.
- Working closely with the Division Technical Director, manage collection of MEL data in the target districts and provide overall leadership and troubleshooting to Partners and Private sectors staffs through capacity building training.
- Conduct data quality assessment (DQA) includes spot checks, cross check, routine project monitoring, to ensure data quality and aggregate data at the sub-region level.
- Conduct brief and cost-effective operational checks on the project to gauge outcomes/impacts and to use data/information to improve on project activities.
- Conduct assessments (rapid cycle evaluation, rapid market assessment, deep dive, impact assessment) and direct involvement of formative research on market system development strategy (MSDS) and social behavior change (SBC).

Key Achievement's: Played leading role in the establishment of Data collection tools, data entry format and Data Analysis tools under BNA project catchment areas and successfully completed formative research by using different tools. Quarterly and yearly routine monitoring survey completion. Doing subset analysis and regular presenting in monthly meeting upon all project staffs at District level.

Organization: World Vision Bangladesh, Nobo Jatra Project, funded by USAID-Food for Peace (FFP)

Position: Monitoring and Evaluation Specialist/Manager

Duration: September 2016 to April 2019

Key Responsibilities:

- Executed, and coordinated overall M&E systems and MIS according to M&E plan and PIRS across six project components (MCHN, WASH, Gender, Agriculture, and livelihoods, DRR and Good Governance) of 3 Consortium partners (WVB, WFP &WI) and 3 co-operative partners (Shushilan, Nabolok & CODEC).
- Worked closely with the M& E Manager to formulate ToR, guideline, specific data collection methods and tools, ensure quality of data, cross-checking, validation & review
- Analyzed data using computer-based software like SPSS/STATA to aggregate findings and shared those to management/ project staffs for decision making.
- Prepared consolidated progress reports on M&E findings for the Management including identification of problems, causes of potential bottlenecks in implementation & providing specific recommendations.
- Identified lessons learned and develop case studies in view of M&E to capture qualitative outputs of the project.
- Conducted and supported capacity building training of consortium and Co-operative partners (CP) staffs on all aspects of data generation, database management, reporting, MIS problem solving, communication, provides guidance within area and level of expertise.
- Accomplished periodic survey, small studies, and research
- Developed field complaints mechanism, related processes, and procedures.

Key Achievement's: Managing 52,606 Households through robust MIS which implementing by 3 consortium partners (World Vision Bangladesh, World Food Programme and Winrock International) & 3 Co-operative partners (Shushilan, Nabolok & CODEC) and completed Mid-term evaluation successfully. Rollout KoboTolbox application through developed 10 quick data collection mobile/Tab tools by using KoBoToolbox in Nobo Jatra Project (NJP).

Organization: IRRI Bangladesh, CSISA-BD Project, funded by USAID-FtF

Position: Officer-Monitoring & Evaluation Duration: April 2013 to September 2015

Key Responsibilities:

- Implemented & monitored overall M&E System of three CGIAR partners (IRRI, CIMMYT and World Fish) & six local partners
- Supervised the regular basis data collection, storage (hard & soft copy), cross checking, validation, analyzing & reviewing data from the project area (FTF zone)
- Contributed to DQA exercise together with the project M&E central team aligned with USAID DQA guideline
- Conduced capacity building for program & partners staff on M&E activities.
- Prepared progress, project semi-annual and annual reports for three lead partners (i.e., IRRI, CIMMYT and World Fish).

Key Achievement's: Managed 38,000 beneficiaries of 3 consortium partners (IRRI, CYMMIT & World Fish) with Access database in an integrated way with reputation and completed external DQA and midterm & final evaluation fruitfully.

Organization: World Vision Bangladesh, Funded by USAID, Korea & Singapore

Position: Monitoring & Evaluation Officer

Duration: April 2010 to April 2013

Key Responsibilities:

- Assisting in development and use appropriate Monitoring Tools to verify the authenticity of the qualitative and quantitative data by field- testing at pre and post implementation of major interventions
- Compiled information and prepared monthly/quarterly/Semi -annual/annual monitoring report (qualitative and quantitative)
- Prepared survey tools, data collection techniques and analysis.
- Developed M&E tools and terms of reference (ToR), coordinated baseline studies and evaluations
- Ensuring proper documentation and reporting of the assessment process and outcomes at Upazila and District level.
- Regular monitoring of Post distribution input.

Key Achievement's: Managed 26,000 beneficiaries by Access database software, completed interim evaluation successfully and facilitated transition workshop of 3 Area development program (Mongla, Chitalmari & Laudob ADP).

Organization: RDRS Bangladesh, Empowering the poor through federations (EPF) Project, Funded by EC

Position: Senior Monitoring & Evaluation Officer

Duration: May 2008 to April 2010

Key Responsibility:

- Established database (both manual and computerized) for EPF Project at district level.
- Conducted case study and contributing to project's other research / studies.
- Ensured collection of field data as per project's M&E framework.
- Prepared reports for submission to the management as required by the project / organization.
- Developed and implemented M&E tools.

Key Achievement's: Played key role in the establishment of **5 Union Jana Tatty Digital Kendra** under Lalmonirhat district using M& E database and after successfully completed piloting work by RDRS Bangladesh Government took the idea and now all Union parishad ICT center is the result of that piloting project.

TRAINING/WORKSHOP RECEIVED

- Four-days Inclusive SPSS Training through Digital MEL Hub & Circle Associates, 2024
- Five-days Inclusive GIS Training through Digital MEL Hub & Circle Associates, 2023
- Five-days Inclusive Kobo Training through Digital MEL Hub & Circle Associates, 2023
- Six-week long training on Emotionally Intelligent Leadership (EIL) in Execudemy, USA, Florida 2023
- Six-day training on Analyzing Data with **Power BI** in Skill Jobs, 2023
- Seven-day training on Inclusive leadership & Leader-in-Me in Execudemy, USA, Florida 2023
- Seventeen-day Webinar on Seventeen separate MEL Related issues through Digital MEL Hub, 2022-2024
- Fourteen-day training on Applied Statistics using **STATA** in Dhaka University, 2021
- Sixteen-day training on Python programming language (Level-1& Level-2) in Data Society-USA, Abt Associates under Data Science Fellowship, Online WebEx Platform, 2021
- Three-day Workshop on Monitoring & Evaluation by TANGO & World Vision Bangladesh, Dhaka 2018
- Three-day training on Communicating an Evidence-based Approach (CEA) writing workshop by World Vision Bangladesh, Khulna 2017
- Five-day training on CSISA-BD Common data base through access program by IRRI- Bangladesh, Dhaka 2014
- Three- day Training on Trainers (TOT) on Facilitation Skills by BRAC, Barisal 2012
- Twelve-day training on Transition Workshop on Sustainable Change and dependency by WVB & WVK, Khulna 2012
- Three-day Training on Humanitarian Accountability Partnership (HAP) by World Vision Bangladesh, Khulna 2011
- Six-day Training on Computer Operation and Information Software management by D-net & RDRS Bangladesh, Dhaka 2008
- Four-day Training on Right Based Approach and Gender organized by DFID & RDRS Bangladesh, Rangpur 2008
- Five-day training on ToT on M&E System with data collection and data analysis organized by M&E Associate & RDRS Bangladesh, Rangpur 2008.

PROFESSIONAL REFERENCE

REFERENCE-I	REFERENCE-2	REFERENCE-3
Nasirul Islam	Bilash Mitra	Md. Rafiqul Islam
Technical Director-Learning & Adapting	MELS Lead , IFDC, CSA Activity	M&E Lead, Titukulane Project, CARE Malawi
Save the Children Bangladesh	27 Suhrowardi Avenue (Level 7),	Pamodzi House, Off Presidential Drive,
Gulshan-2, Dhaka, Bangladesh	Baridhara Diplomatic Zone, Dhaka	Private Bag A 89, Lilongwe Malawi
E-Mail: nasiruldu@gmail.com	E-Mail: bilm0503@yahoo.com	E-mail: rafique.islam@care.org
Cell No.: +8801779765993	Cell No: +8801712737640	Cell: +265 (0) 887 387 973

Initiative, Utilization and Connection with MEL people:

WhatsApp Group Link (Digital MEL Hub): https://chat.whatsapp.com/ljvfl07mipe]Yd6WFjVOow Facebook Group Link (Digital MEL Hub): https://www.facebook.com/groups/2006413989525683

LinkedIn Group Link (Digital MEL Hub): https://www.linkedin.com/groups/14009477

YouTube Channel (Digital MEL Hub): https://youtube.com/@digitalmelhub8561?si=V7iTuYm4klmnw0dF Website (To get all previous webinar recording): https://circleassociatesbd.org/digital-melhub-webinars

Colytoseain

Date: April 28, 2024